A Guide to the Meikleham-Randolph-Trist-Coolidge Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7007
Meikleham-Randolph-Trist-Coolidge Family Papers 1799-1887
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7007
52 items
Robert W. Graves
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Library purchased this collection (# 7007 ) from Robert W. Graves of Delray Beach, Florida on March 15, 1963.
Scope and Content
This collection of ca. 100 items, 1799-1887 and n.d., consists chiefly of correspondence among the extended members of the Randolph family, descendants of Thomas Jefferson. The majority of the correspondence is between the granddaughter of Thomas Jefferson, Septimia Anna Cary (Randolph) Meikleham(1814-1887) and her siblings, Virginia Jefferson (Randolph) Trist(1801-1882), Cornelia Jefferson Randolph(1799-1871), Ellen Wayles (Randolph) Coolidge(1796-1876), and Meriwether Lewis Randolph(1810-1837). Correspondents also include Septimia's nieces and nephews, Martha Jefferson (Trist) Burke(1826-1915), Ellen R. (Coolidge) Dwight(1826-1894), Isaetta Carter (Randolph) Hubard(1835-1888), and Lewis Carter Randolph(1838-1887); her son, William Moreland Meikleham(1839-1889); and her grandsons, Thomas Mann Randolph Meikleham(1869-1954) and Henry Parish Meikleham(1872-1937).
Letters from Septimia Randolph in Pensacola, Florida, December 27, n.y. and January 26, 1838, tell about her adventurous trip to the area, her social life, and how various groups of people--"native Creoles," "whites," "quadroons," and "negroes"--were segregated in a theater. After leaving Pensacola, Septimia went to Havana, Cuba to be with her sister, (Randolph) Trist and her family. While there, she met and married David Scott Meikleham(1804-1849). Letters from Havana, February 16, 1838, November 3, 1839, and June 15, 1840, discuss life there, including living outside of the city walls. Later, on October 22, [1843], Septimia writes from Glasgow, Scotland about its people and land, and describes her visits to Edin Castle, Holyrood Palace, and the Highlands.
During June and July of 1882, correspondence between Septimia (Randolph) Meikleham and family members was concerned with congressional bills to aid Thomas Jefferson's heirs, particularly his granddaughter, Septimia, and the possible removal of Thomas Jefferson's remains from Monticello to Washington, D. C. A letter, August 4, n.y., from Virginia (Randolph) Trist discusses the new owner of Monticello, Jefferson Michael [sic] Levy, and the work he is having done on the estate.
A good source for information on the descendants of Thomas Jefferson is Collected Papers of the Monticello Association, edited by George Green Shackelford, (The Monticello Association, Charlottesville, Virginia, 1984). Biographies and genealogical charts are included.
Container List
- "Inventory of my Cloths [sic]," written by Alice Scott, 1799 Dec 17; AMs
- Report of school grades for Septimia Anna Cary Randolph, [1820s] Apr 21
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph to Mrs. T. J. [Jane Hollins Nicholas] Randolph, 1828 Feb 28; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph to [Meriwether] Lewis Randolph, 1829 [Oct] 25; ALS
- Meriwether Lewis Randolph to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph, 1830 July 23; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph to Susan B. Coolidge, 1832 July 8; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph to [Martha Jefferson] Randolph, [1835] Feb 11; ALS
- Invitation to Miss Septimia Randolph to a party at the University of Virginia, [1836] Oct 7
- Bill of Sale to Miss Randolph from Alex T. Stewart & Company, 1837 June 19
- [ Septimia Anna Cary Randolph] to Susan B. Coolidge, 1838 Jan 6; AL
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph to Susan B. Coolidge, 1838 Feb 16; ALS
- Bill of Sale to Miss Randolph from Alex T. Stewart & Company, 1838 June 15
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge, 1839 Nov 3; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to [Virginia Jefferson Randolph] Trist, 1840 June 15; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, [1842] May 12; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, [1843] Oct 22; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to [ Martha Jefferson Trist], [1843]; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, 1844 Jan 18; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, [1844] Mar 28; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Martha Jefferson Trist, 1848 Sep 5; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Martha JeffersonTrist, [1849] Aug 29; ALS
- "Julia" to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, [1849] Nov 20; ALS
- E. A. Meikleham to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, 1853 Oct 1; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, [1854] July 23; ALS
- E. A. Meikleham to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, 1854 July 30; ALS
- E. A. Meikleham to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, 1855 Jan 3; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, 1855 Sep 1; ALS
- A critique of an article in the New York Daily Tribune of July 26, 1869 related to Thomas Jefferson, and a description of Monticello, AMs
- Ellen W[ayles Randolph] Coolidge to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, 1870 Oct 1; ALS
- Bill of Sale for land to Mary J. Randolph included in the will of Cornelia Jefferson Randolph, 1871 Feb 24; AMs
- Draft of a deed of sale for house (Walnutfield) and land to Mary J. Randolph, as provided in the will of Cornelia Jefferson Randolph, 1871 July 17; AMs
- William [Moreland Meikleham] to [Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham], w/env., 1877 Sep 10; ALS
- William Moreland Meikleham to [Esther] Alice Meikleham, w/env., 1877 Sep 21; ALS
- William Moreland Meikleham to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, w/env., 1877 Oct 9; ALS
- V[irginia] J[efferson] [Randolph] Trist to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, 1878 Nov 20; ALS
- Virginia Jefferson Randolph Trist to E. A. Meikleham, 1879 June 12; ALS
- Virginia Jefferson Randolph Trist to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, 1882 Feb 7; ALS
- L[ewis] C[arter] R[andolph] to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, 1882 June 7; ALS
- E [ ? ] H[ ? ] to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, w/env., [1882] June 10; ALS
- Ellen R. [Coolidge] D[wight] to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, w/env., 1882 June 15; ALS
- E[lizabeth] M. Eppes, S[usan] F[rances] [Eppes] Craig, and N[icholas] W[are] Eppes to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, w/env., 1882 July 18; ALS
- [Thomas Mann] Randolph [Meikleham] to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, 1885 Dec 30; ALS
- Thomas Mann Randolph Meikleham to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, 1887 Jan 3; ALS
- John B. Randolph to E. A. Meikleham, 1887 Sep 15; ALS
- Invitation to "Mrs. Randolph and Ladies" to a Ball at the Central Masonic Hall, n.y. Jan 8
- Invitation to Miss Septimia Randolph for the Anniversary Ball of the Victory of New Orleans, n.y. Jan 8
- Isaetta C[arter] [Randolph] Hubard to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, n.y. Feb 16; ANS
- Virginia Jefferson Randolph Trist and C[ornelia] J[efferson] R[andolph] to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, n.y. Mar 9; ALS
- Jemima Hapgood to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, n.y. May 23; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, n.y. May 28; ALS
- Virginia Jefferson Randolph Trist and M[artha] J[efferson] T[rist] Burke to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, n.y. May 29; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, n.y. Jun 1; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, n.y. Jun 12; ALS
- Virginia Jefferson Randolph Trist to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, n.y. Jun 17; ALS
- Virginia Jefferson Randolph Trist to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, n.y. Jul 6; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, n.y. Jul 15; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, n.y. Jul 27; ALS
- Virginia Jefferson Randolph Trist to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, n.y. Aug 1; ALS
- Virginia Jefferson Randolph Trist to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, n.y. Aug 4; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, n.y. Aug 6; ALS
- Unidentified to "Alice" [E. A. Meikleham], n.y. Aug 25; AL
- Virginia Jefferson Randolph Trist to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, n.y. Sep 3; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, n.y. Sep 18; ALS
- Virginia Jefferson Randolph Trist to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, n.y. Sep 28; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, n.y. Oct 18; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, n.y. Nov 9; ALS
- Virginia Jefferson Randolph Trist to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, n.y. Nov 30; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Susan B. Coolidge Lyman, n.y. Dec 4; ALS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph to [Martha Jefferson Randolph], n.y. Dec 27; ALS
- H[enry] P[arish] M[eikleham] to "Grandma" [Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham], n.y. Dec 31; ALS
- Virginia Jefferson Randolph Trist to Martha Jefferson Randolph, Wednesday; ALS
- D[avid] S[cott] Meikleham to "Mama", Friday; ALS
- E[llen] W[ayles] [Randolph] Coolidge to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph, ALS
- Ellen Wayles Randolph Coolidge to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham, ALS
- Mary P. Randolph to Martha [Jefferson] Randolph, ANS
- C[ornelia] J[efferson] R[andolph] to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph, ANS
- "Matilda" to Septimia Anna Cary Randolph, 7 AnsS
- Septimia Anna Cary Randolph Meikleham to Virginia Jefferson Randolph Trist(fragment), ALS
- Essay on Spanish history, n.d.; AMs
- Notes on Spanish history, n.d.; AMs
- Poem with notes in Spanish, n.d.; AMs
- Composition book with [original?] poems, by unknown author, signed E.J.M. on first page, n.d.; AMs
- Pencil drawings of floor plan [for addition to a house?], n.d.; 8 items
- Covers of notebook belonging to "Septimia Randolph, Monticello, Dec 7, 1818"
- Front cover of scrapbook with printed sketches on inside, including one of Susannah Randolph
- Calling cards, n.d.; 5 items
- Pamphlet, "Lady Washington's Reception Day," a description of a painting by D. Huntington, Printed
- Eleanora Jefferson Meikleham, and unidentified man, Photographs
- Music sheets with autograph words and melody, 2 items